In the last few videos, we've talked about managing registers. In this video, we're
在上几个视频中，我们讨论了如何管理寄存器。在这段视频中，我们将
going take a few moments to talk about another very important resource, the cache
我将花几分钟时间来讨论另一项非常重要的资源，即缓存
and what compilers can and can't do to manage them. Modern computer systems have
以及编译器可以和不能做什么来管理它们。现代计算机系统具有
quite elaborate memory hierarchies. And so, if we were to start at the closest
相当精细的内存层次结构。所以，如果我们从最近的
level to the processor itself, we would find that on the chip there are some
级别到处理器本身，我们会发现芯片上有一些
number of registers. And these are very fast access. So, typically that can be
寄存器数量。这些都是非常快速的访问。因此，通常情况下，这可以是
accessed in a single cycle so at the same rate as the clock frequency. And the
在单个周期内以与时钟频率相同的速率访问。以及
problem is that it's very expensive to build such high performance memory. And
问题是，构建如此高性能的内存非常昂贵。和
so, we don't get to have very much of it, typically. You know, you might have 256,
所以，通常情况下，我们不会拥有太多。你知道，你可能有256个，
say, to 8K bytes of registers total available to you on a given processor.
比方说，在给定的处理器上总共有8K字节的寄存器可供您使用。
Now, a very significant portion of the die area and the modern processor would be
现在，芯片面积和现代处理器的很大一部分将是
devoted to the cache. And the cache is also quite high performance but not quite
全身心投入到高速缓存中。缓存的性能也相当高，但不是很高
as high performance as registers. Maybe on average, it would take three cycles just
与寄存器一样的高性能。也许平均下来，光是它就需要三个周期
service something from the cache but you get a lot more of it. And modern
从缓存中提供服务，但你会得到更多。而且很现代
processors would have up to a megabyte of cache. Then, much further away from the
处理器将拥有高达1兆字节的高速缓存。然后，在更远的地方
processor is the main memory, the DRAM, and this is much more expensive to
处理器是主内存，也就是DRAM，这要昂贵得多
allocate to access in time you know, typical values would be twenty to 100
要及时分配访问权限，典型值为20到100
cycles and I think, you know, it's more on 100 toward the 120 these days in most
循环，我认为，你知道，这些天来大多数人都在100到120之间
processors but you get quite a lot of it. You get between 32 megabytes. That would
处理器，但是你得到了相当多的处理器。大小在32兆字节之间。那将会是
be fairly small machine up to four gigabytes for maximally provisions
相当小的计算机，最高可达4 GB，可提供最多4 GB的资源
processor. And finally, farthest away is typically disk. And this takes a very,
处理器。最后，最远的通常是磁盘。这需要非常，
very long time to get to hundreds of thousands or millions of cycles but you
需要很长时间才能达到几十万或几百万个周期，但是你
can have enormous amounts of storage out there, gigabytes to terabytes of storage.
可以有巨大的存储空间，从千兆字节到兆兆字节。
As I said, there are limitations on the size and speed of registers and caches.
正如我所说的，寄存器和高速缓存的大小和速度是有限制的。
And these are limited as much by power actually as, as anything e lse these days.
而这些实际上和现在的任何电子产品一样，都受到了权力的限制。
And I, and so it's, you know, very important people would like to have as
我，所以，你知道，非常重要的人希望
much register and cache as possible but there are real constraints on how big and
尽可能多的寄存器和高速缓存，但有多大和
how fast we can make these relative to the speeds of the processors. Now
相对于处理器的速度，我们能以多快的速度完成这些任务。现在
unfortunately, the cost of a cache miss is very high as we saw in the previous slide.
不幸的是，正如我们在上一张幻灯片中看到的那样，缓存未命中的成本非常高。
If you, you could get something in a couple of cycles from the cache. But if
如果你，你可以在几个周期内从缓存中得到一些东西。但是如果
it's not in the cache, then it could take you a couple of orders of magnitude longer
它不在缓存中，那么它可能会花费你几个数量级的时间
to get it out of the main memory. And so for this reason people, you know, try to
将其从主存储器中取出。因此，出于这个原因，人们，你知道，试着
build caches in between the processor and the main memory to hide that latency of
在处理器和主内存之间构建缓存，以隐藏
the main memory so that most of the data is in the cache. And typically, it
主存储器，以便大部分数据都在高速缓存中。通常情况下，它
requires more than one level of cache these days to match a fast processor well
目前需要多个级别的高速缓存才能很好地匹配快速处理器
with the speed of a very large main memory. So, you know, very common now to
具有非常大的主存储器的速度。所以，你知道，现在很常见的
have two levels of cache and processors and some processors even have three levels
有两级高速缓存和处理器，有些处理器甚至有三级
of cache. So the bottom line is that it's very important to for high performance to
缓存的大小。所以底线是，要想获得高性能，非常重要的一点是
manage these resources properly. Particular to manage the registers and the
正确管理这些资源。特定于管理寄存器和
cache as well if you want your program to perform well. Compilers have become very
如果您希望您的程序运行良好，也可以使用缓存。编译器已经变得非常
good in managing registers and in fact, I think today, most people would agree that
擅长管理登记簿，事实上，我想今天，大多数人都会同意这一点
for almost all programs, compilers do a better job at managing registers than
对于几乎所有程序，编译器在管理寄存器方面比
programmers can. And so, it's very worthwhile to leave the job of allocating
程序员可以。因此，离开分配工作是非常值得的
registers or assigning registers to the compiler. However, compilers are not good
寄存器或将寄存器分配给编译器。但是，编译器不是很好。
at managing caches. And while there's a little bit that compilers can do and
管理高速缓存。虽然有一些编译器可以做的事情，但是
that's what we're going to talk about in this rest of this video for the most part,
这就是我们将在这段视频的睡觉中谈论的大部分内容，
if programmers want to get good cache performance, they have to understand the
如果程序员想要获得良好的缓存性能，他们必须了解
behavior of the cache is on the machine and have to understand what their program
缓存的行为在机器上，并且必须了解他们的程序是什么
is doing, you have to understand a little bit about what the compiler is capable of
，您必须稍微了解一下编译器的功能。
doing and then they still have to , write the program in such a way that is going
这样做，然后他们仍然必须，以这样一种方式来编写程序
to, to be cache friendly. So, it's still very much an open question. How much a
TO，以便于缓存。所以，这在很大程度上仍然是一个悬而未决的问题。一张多少钱？
compiler can do to improve cache performance? Although, there are a few
编译器可以做些什么来提高缓存性能？不过，还是有几个
things that we've found compilers can do reliably. So, to see one of those things
我们发现编译器可以可靠地做的事情。所以，要想看到这些东西中的一件
that compilers can actually do let's take a look at this example loop. So, what we
编译器实际上可以做的事情，让我们来看看这个示例循环。所以，我们要做的是
have here, we have an outer loop on j and inner loop on i and then in each iteration
在这里，我们在j上有一个外循环，在i上有一个内循环，然后在每次迭代中
of the inner loop we're reading from , some vector you know, performing some
我们正在读取的内部循环的一些向量，你知道的，执行一些
computational net value and storing the results into the ith element of the A
计算净值并将结果存储到A的第i个元素中
vector. Now, as it turns out, this particular program has really, really
矢量。现在，事实证明，这个特别的项目真的，真的
terrible cache performance. This is going to behave very badly. And so, let's think
缓存性能极差。这将会表现得非常糟糕。所以，让我们想一想
about what's going to happen. So, let's imagine our cache, you know, as some block
关于将要发生的事情。所以，让我们想象一下我们的缓存，你知道，就像一些挡路
of memory, okay. And so, what's going to happen here. I mean, what's, what's the
记忆，好的。那么，这里会发生什么。我是说，怎么，怎么回事
first iteration going to be? Well, we're going to, you know load and, store some
第一次迭代会是什么？嗯，我们要，你知道的，装载和储存一些
function of that into . And so, what's going to get loaded into the cache is and
功能就是把它变成。因此，要加载到缓存中的是和
. All right, let's assume they just go into different elements in this just for
。好的，让我们假设它们只是进入了不同的元素，只是为了
the sake of argument, let's say they land in the first two elements in the cache.
为了便于讨论，我们假设它们位于缓存中的前两个元素中。
And then we're going to do the second iteration of this and, we'll, we'll load
然后我们要做这个的第二次迭代，我们会，我们会加载
and write it into and so and will be loaded into the cache, all right and so
并将其写入和，然后将其加载到高速缓存中，好的，等等
on. And this will repeat over and over and over again, loading one element of a and
在……上面。这将一遍又一遍地重复，加载AND的一个元素
one element of b the important thing to notice is that all of these references to
b的一个要素需要注意的重要一点是，所有这些引用
a and to b are misses, okay. Every single one of these is a cache miss because on
A和TO B都错过了，好吗？其中每一个都是缓存未命中，因为打开
each iteration of the loop we refer to new elements, okay. So, we're not referring to
循环的每一次迭代我们都引用新的元素，好的。所以，我们指的不是
the same elements as we were on the previous ones. So, now let's ignore for
这些元素与我们在前几个元素上所用的相同。所以，现在让我们忽略
the moment the fact that there may be multiple elements in the same cache line,
在同一高速缓存线中可能存在多个元素的事实的瞬间，
okay. So, some of you probably are aware already. That when we fetch data from
好吧。所以，你们中的一些人可能已经意识到了。当我们从
memory we don't just fetch the one word, okay. So, typically when we refer to for
记住，我们不能只取一个词，好吗？因此，通常当我们提到for时
example you know, is stored here will fetch an entire cache line which will be
例如，存储在此处的将提取整个缓存线，该缓存线将
some block of memory and that may well have, you know, other elements of b in it.
一些挡路的记忆，你知道，这里面很可能有其他的b元素。
So, we might get a couple other elements of b into the cache at the same time but
因此，我们可能会同时将b的其他几个元素放入高速缓存，但是
the important thing here is that on every iteration of the loop, we're referring to
这里重要的是，在循环的每一次迭代中，我们指的是
fresh data, okay. And, and if these data values are large enough, if they take up
最新数据，好的。如果这些数据值足够大，如果它们占用
an entire cache line, then each iteration of the loop is going to be a cache miss
整个高速缓存线，则循环的每个迭代都将是高速缓存未命中
for both elements, and we won't get any benefit of the cache. And this loop will
对于这两个元素，我们不会从缓存中获得任何好处。这个循环将会
run at the rate of at the rate of the main memory and not at the rate of the cache.
以主内存的速率运行，而不是以高速缓存的速率运行。
Now, the other thing that's important here is that this loop bound here is very large
现在，另一件重要的事情是，这里的循环边界非常大
and I picked it to be very large to suggest that it's much larger than the
我把它选得很大是为了表明它比
size of the cache. So, as we get towards the end of the loop what's going to happen
缓存的大小。所以，当我们到达循环的末尾时，会发生什么
is we will have filled up the whole cache, so this whole cache will be filled with
我们将填满整个高速缓存，因此整个高速缓存将被填满
values from a and b, and then it's going to start clobbering values that are
来自a和b的值，然后它将开始重击符合以下条件的值
already in the cache. And if this loop, you know, if the size of these vectors,
已经在缓存中了。如果这个循环，你知道，如果这些向量的大小，
let's say twice the size of the cache by the time we come around and complete the
比方说，当我们来到这里并完成以下操作时，缓存的大小是原来的两倍
entire execution of the. Inner loop. What's in the cache is the second half of
整个执行过程。内循环。在缓存里的是后半部分的
the a and b arrays, it's not the first half of the a and b arrays. And so, then
a和b数组，它不是a和b数组的前半部分。所以，那么
when we go back around and execute another iteration of the outer loop, now what's in
当我们返回并执行外部循环的另一个迭代时，现在
the cache is also, going to be not the data that we're referencing. And so when
缓存也不会是我们引用的数据。所以当
we come back around and begin the execution of the inner loop the second
我们返回并开始执行第二个内循环
time. And we refer to and, and, and . What's in the cache is the values from the
时间到了。我们指的是和，和，和。缓存中的值来自
high numbered elements of the a and b vector and not the low numbered elements.
a和b向量中编号较高的元素，而不是编号较低的元素。
And so, these references are all misses again. And so, the, the basic problem with
因此，这些引用又都是未命中的。所以，最基本的问题是
this loop is, a loop that's structured like this, is that almost every memory
这个循环是，一个这样结构的循环，几乎每一个记忆
reference and if, and if the data values are big enough again that they fill an
引用和If，并且如果数据值再次足够大，则它们将填充
entire cache line then it will be every single memory reference is a cache miss.
整个高速缓存线，那么它将是每个单个存储器引用都是高速缓存未命中。
Now, instead, let's consider an alternative structure for the same
现在，取而代之的是，让我们考虑一种相同的替代结构
program. Here, I've put the i loop at as the outer loop and the j loop as the inner
程序。在这里，我将i循环作为外部循环，将j循环作为内部循环
loop. And here what we do is we load . And we write and then we repeat that
循环。我们现在要做的就是装载。然后我们写下来，然后我们重复这个过程
computation ten times on the same data values. And so here we'll get excellent
对相同的数据值进行十次计算。所以在这里我们会变得很棒
cash performance. We'll, we'll have a miss on the first reference, but then on the
现金业绩。我们会，我们会错过第一次引用，但是在接下来的
subsequent nine references the data will be in the cache or will completely exhaust
随后的九个引用数据将在缓存中或将完全耗尽
our computation on those particular a and b values. And then we'll go on to the next
我们对这些特殊的a和b值的计算。然后我们将继续下一个
a and b values. We'll finish the inner loop and go on to the other and do one
a和b值。我们将完成内循环，然后转到另一个循环，做一个
more iteration of the outer loop. And so, the advantage of this structure is that it
外部循环的更多迭代。因此，这种结构的优点是它
brings the data into the cache and then it uses that data as much as possible, before
将数据放入高速缓存，然后在此之前尽可能多地使用该数据
going on to the next data. Rather than doing a little bit on every data item and
接下来是下一个数据。而不是在每个数据项上都做一点工作，
then going back, you know, doing one pass and then going back and sweeping over all
然后往回走，你知道的，做一次传球，然后往回走，横扫所有
items, items again and doing another little bit. Alright, so this particular
一件一件，一件一件，再做一点。好的，那么这个特别的
structure, where we've exchanged the order of the outer loops sorry, exchanged the
结构，在该结构中，我们交换了外部循环的顺序对不起，它交换了
order of the inner and outer loops, it computes exactly the same thing but it has
内部循环和外部循环的顺序，它计算的是完全相同的东西，但是它
much better cache behavior. And it probably run more than ten times faster.
更好的缓存行为。而且它的运行速度可能要快十倍以上。
Now compilers can preform this simple loop interchange optimization. This particular
现在编译器可以执行这个简单的循环交换优化。这个特别的
kind of optimization is called loop interchange, where you just switch in the
一种优化称为循环交换，在这种情况下您只需切换到
order of loops. In this particular case, it's very easy to see that that's legal
循环顺序。在这种情况下，很容易看出这是合法的
and the compiler could actually figure it out. Not many compilers actually implement
而编译器实际上可以计算出它。没有多少编译器真正实现
this optimization because in general, it's not easy to decide whe ther you can
这种优化是因为通常不容易决定是否可以
reverse the orders of, of the loops. And so usually, a programmer would have to
颠倒循环、循环的顺序。所以通常情况下，程序员必须
figure out that they wanted to do this, in order to improve the performance in the
弄清楚他们想要这样做，是为了提高